"Robam kbach boran,"
روبام كباك بوران
or the art of Khmer classical dance,
أو فن رقص الخمير الكلاسيكي.
is more than 1,000 years old.
عمره اكثر من 1000 سنة.
It was developed as a prayer in movement
تم تطويره كحركة للصلاة
for rain and fertility,
للأمطار و الخصوبة
and a prosperity that this meant for an agricultural society.
والإزدهار الذي يعني المجتمع الزراعي
Dancers who were both men and women
الراقصين الذين كانوا رجالا ونساء
were offered to temples
عرضوا على المعابد
where they served as living bridges between heaven and earth.
حيث خدموا كجسور حية بين الجنة والأرض.
Their dancing bodies carried the prayers of the people up to the gods,
وحملت أجسادهم الراقصة صلوات الناس إلى الألهة
and the will of the deities was delivered back through them
وإرادة الالهة تم تسليمها من خلالهم
to the people and the land.
إلى الناس والأرض.
There are a lot of curves in Khmer dance.
هناك الكثير من الإنحناء في رقص الخمير.
Our backs are arched,
تتقوس ظهورنا
our knees are bent,
وتنثني ركبتينا
our toes are curled,
وتنثني أصابع أقدامنا
our elbows are hyperflexed
وينثني مرفقينا بشدة
and our fingers are curved backwards.
وتنحني أصابع يدينا للخلف
All of these curves create a serpentine impression,
كل هذه المنحنيات تشكل انطباع افعواني
and this is important because before the introduction of major religions,
وهذا مهم لأنه قبل ادخال الديانات الرئيسية
Khmers, and people all over the world practiced animism.
الخمير وكل الناس حول العالم مارسوا الأرواحية
Serpents were especially important in this belief system
كانت الثعابين مهمة جداً في هذا المعتقد
because in their fluid, curvilinear movement,
لأنه في حركتها المائية كثيرة الإنحناء
they mimicked the flow of water.
تقلد تدفق المياه
So to invoke the serpent in your dancing body then
لذلك تمثيل حركة الأفعى عبر جسدك الراقص
was to conjure the image of rivers cutting across the earth:
هو إستحضار صورة الأنهار المتدفقة عبر الأرض
inspire the flow of life-giving waters.
و إلهام طاقة المياه الواهبة للحياة
As you can see then,
كما سأريكم
Khmer classical dance is a transformation of nature,
رقص الخمير الكلاسيكي هو تحول لطبيعة
of both the physical world around us and of our own internal universe.
العالم الظاهر حولنا و أكواننا الداخلية
We have four primary hand gestures that we use.
لدينا اربعة إيماءات يدوية رئيسية
Can we do them together?
هل نقوم بها معاً؟
Yeah? OK.
حسناً؟
This is a tree.
هذه شجرة
That tree will grow,
و هذه الشجرة ستنموا
and then it will have leaves.
و بعدها ستحظى بالأوراق
After it has leaves,
و بعد ذلك
it'll have flowers,
سيكون لديها زهور
and after it has flowers,
و بعد الزهور سيكون لديها
it'll have fruit.
فواكه
That fruit will drop
و تلك الفاكهه ستقع
and a new tree will grow.
و شجرة جديدة ستنموا
And in those four gestures
و في هذه الإيماءات الأربعة
is the cycle of life.
تتشكل دائرة الحياة
These four gestures are then used
ثم تُستخدم الإيماءات الأربعة بعد ذلك
to create a whole entire language with which dancers express themselves.
في تكوين لغة يعبر بها الراقصين عبر اجسادهم
So for example,
مثال على ذلك:
I can say,
استطيع ان اقول
"I."
أنـا
In dance that would be ...
عندما أجسدها بالرقص ستكون
Or I can say ...
او قد اقول
"Hey you, come here, come here."
"أنت، تعال إلى هنا"
In dance ...
بالرقص..
"Come here,"
"تعال هنا"
or, "Go, go."
أو "إذهب، إذهب"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"Go."
"إذهب"
And everything from ...
و كل شيء من...
love ...
الحب...
to sadness,
الحزن،
to --
إلى..
(Stomping)
(دوس)
anger
الغضب
can be expressed through the dance as well.
يمكن تعبيره بالرقص ايضاً
There's a certain magic
هنالك سحر خاص
in the way that things are filtered, transformed and put together
في تنقيح الأشياء و تحويلها ثم تجميعها
to create limitless possibilities in art.
لخلق إمكانيات لامنتهية في صورة الفن
The Khmer word for art,
المفرد الخميري للفن هو
silapak,
فيلاباك
in fact, at its root, means "magic."
و معناه الجذري هو "السحر"
The artist --
الفنان
the silapakar,
الفيلاباكار
or the silapakarani, then,
او الفيلاباكاراني بالأحرى
is nothing short of a magician.
هو لا شيء اخر سوى ساحراً
I am very proud to say
و أنـا فخور جداً لأقول
that I belong to a long line of magicians,
أنني انتمي الى تاريخ طويل من الساحرين
from my teacher, Sophiline Cheam Shapiro,
من معلمتي، سوفيا شين شابيرو
to her teachers who were stars in the royal palace,
إلى معلميها النجوم في القصرالملكي
to the ancient dancers of Angkor
و إلى راقصين أنقور القدماء
and to the primal villagers
و حتى القرويين الأصليين
from which the art form originally took life.
حيث تجسد هذا الفن هناك لأول مره
That said,
و بمعرفة هذا
our cherished heritage was once almost completely destroyed.
إرثنا الغالي كان عرضة لخطر التدمير بالكامل
If you are wearing glasses,
إن كنت ترتدي النظارات
please stand up.
إنهض من فضلك
If you speak more than one language,
اذا تتحدث اكثر من لغة واحدة
If you have light skin,
اذا كانت بشرتك فاتحة
please stand up.
إنهض من فضلك
Your glasses meant that you could afford health care.
نظاراتك تدل على قدرتك لتلقي الرعاية الصحية
That second or third language you spoke indicated your elite education.
لغاتك الإضافية تدل على تعليمك العالي
Your light skin meant you didn't have to work beneath the sun.
و بشرتك الفاتحة تعني انك لم تكدح تحت الشمس
Under the Khmer Rouge,
تحت حكم الخمير الحمر
who took over Cambodia from 1975 to 1979,
اللذين استولوا على كمبوديا من 1965 إلى 1979
we would all be dead now,
كنا سنموت جميعاً الان
targeted because of our assumed privilege.
مستهدفين بسبب إمتيازنا المزعوم
You see,
لأن
the Khmer Rouge looked to Cambodia,
الخمير الاحمر نظروا الى كمبوديا
and they saw centuries of rigid inequality.
نظروا الى كمبوديا فوجدوا قرون من الظلم
The king and the few elites around him
الملك و القليل من النخبه حوله
had all the pleasures and comforts of the world
إمتلكوا جميع سبل الراحة و المتعة بالعالم
while the mass majority suffered from backbreaking labor
في حين أن الأغلبية عانت من العمل الشاق
and harsh poverty.
و من فقر قاسي
You don't need a history book to see that this is true.
لا تحتاج كتاب تاريخ لترى حقيقة ذلك
The Khmer word for "I,"
المفرد الخمري لكلمة "أنا"
for "me,"
هي
is khnhom.
خونوم
This very same word can also mean "slave"
و الكلمة ذاتها لها معنى اخر وهي "عبد"
and dancers were in fact known as knhom preah robam,
الراقصون كانوا يعرفون بإسم خونوم بريهيبام
or "slaves of the sacred dance."
أو "عبيد الرقصة المقدسة"
The Khmer Rouge sought to end slavery in Cambodia,
أراد الخمير الحمر إنهاء العبودية بكمبوديا
yet somehow they turned everyone into slaves to do it.
ولكنهم جعلوا من الكل عبيداً لأجل مرادهم
They became the oppression that they sought to end.
و اصبحوا القمع اللذي سعوا التخلص منه
They evacuated the capital
قاموا بإخلاء العاصمة
and forced people into labor camps.
و أجبروا الناس بمخيمات العمل
They tore families apart
مزقوا العوائل
and brainwashed children against their own parents.
و غسلوا أدمغة الأطفال ضد أهاليهم
Everywhere, people were dying and being killed,
كان الناس يموتون و يقتلون بكل مكان
losing their lives from disease,
يخسرون حياتهم للمرض
overwork,
العمل الزائد عن الحد
execution and starvation.
الإعدام و المجاعة
The result of this is that an entire third of Cambodia's population was lost
نتيجة لذلك خسرت كمبوديا ثلث سكانها
in less than four years,
في أقل من أربعة سنين
and in that number were 90 percent of Khmer dance artists.
و من بينهم 90% كانوا فنانين الرقص الخميري
In other words,
بصياغة اخرى
nine out of 10 visions for the tradition and future were lost.
خُسرت 9 من كل 10 رؤيات للتقليد و المستقبل
Thankfully, however,
ولكن من حسن الحظ
it was my teacher's teachers,
معلمات معلماتي
Chea Samy, Soth Sam On and Chheng Phon,
شيا سامي، سوث سام أون، و تشينغ بونغ
who would lead the revival of the art form
قادوا حركة إعادة إحياء هذا الفن
from the ashes of war and genocide:
من تحت حطام الحرب و الإبادة الجماعية
one student,
تلميذ واحد،
one gesture,
إيمائة واحدة،
one dance at a time.
رقصة واحدة، كلاً على حدى
They wrote the love,
كتبوا بها الحب
magic,
السحر
beauty,
الجمال
history and philosophy of our lineage
تاريخ و فلسفة نسبنا
into the bodies of the next generation.
على أجساد الجيل التالي
Nearly 40 years later,
و بعد 40 سنة
Khmer classical dance has been revived to new heights.
عاد الرقص الخميري الكلاسيكي بمستوى عالي
Yet somehow it still exists in a vulnerable environment.
ولكن لا يزال موجود ببيئة ضعيفة
The disastrous effects of war still haunt Khmer people today.
تأثير الحرب المدمر لايزال يسكن شعب المنطقة
It is written in our bodies,
إنه مكتوب على اجسادنا
manifested in a genetic passage of PTSD
مجسد في اضطراب ما بعد الصدمة الوراثي
and in families facing cyclical poverty
و بالعوائل التي تعاني الفقر المستمر
and immense cultural rifts and language barriers.
و بالخلافات الثقافية و حواجز اللغة
Yet beauty is a most resilient thing.
ولكن الجمال من اكثر الاشياء مقاومة
Beauty has this ability to grow anywhere and everywhere
الجمال يملك قدرة النمو بأي مكان و بكل مكان
at any time.
و بأي وقت
Beauty is what connects people through time and place.
الجمال هو ما يجمع الناس عبر الزمان والمكان
Beauty is a liberation from suffering.
الجمال هو تحرر من المعاناة
As Khmer artists work to revive our culture and country,
في محاولتنا لإعادة إحياء بلدنا و ثقافتنا
we find that there are many paths in which to move forward into the future.
نجد بأن الطرق لمستقبل أفضل متعددة
And in a tradition where we often don't know the dancer's names,
و بتقاليد كنا لا نعرف بها اسماء الأشخاص
who they were,
من كانوا
what their lives were like,
و كيف كانت حياتهم
what they felt,
بماذا شعروا
let me propose that we move forward honestly and openly from "khnhom."
برأيي نحن تخطينا "خونوم" بقوة
Khnhom not as in slave,
خونوم ليس بمعنى عبد
but as in conscious service.
ولكن بمعنى تقديم الخدمة بإختيار
Khnhom:
خونوم
"I,"
انا
"flowering."
أزدهر
My name is Prumsodun Ok.
إسمي بروسمن اوك
I am Khmer,
انا خميري
and I am American.
و انا امريكي
I am the child of refugees,
انا ابن عائلة مهاجرة
a creator, a healer,
صانع، و معالج
and a builder of bridges.
و باني للجسور
I am my teacher's first male student
انا اول تلميذ ذكر لمعلمتي
in a tradition understood by many as female,
في تقليد مشهور بأنه للإناث
and I founded Cambodia's first gay dance company.
و أسست أول شركة كمبودية للراقصين المثليين
I am the incarnation of the beauty, dreams and power
انا تجسيد للجمال و الاحلام و القوة
of those who came before me.
لمن سبقني
The convergence of past, present and future,
نقطة إلتقاء الماضي و الحاضر و المستقبل
and of individual and collective.
على مستوى الفرد و الجمع
Let me then play that ancient and ageless role
دعني أؤدي دور القديم اللذي لا يفنى
of the artist as messenger,
وهو دور الفنان الرسول
by sharing the words of Chheng Phon
بمشاركة كلمات تشينن بونغ
"A garden with only one type of flower,
"حديقة بنوع واحد من الأزهار فقط
or flowers of only one color,
أو مجموعة من الأزهار بلون واحد
is no good."
لا فائدة منها"
This is a reminder that our strength,
هذا تذكير بأن قوتنا
growth,
نضجنا
survival
نجاتنا
and very existence,
و وجودنا بحد ذاته
lies in diversity.
يكمن في التنوع
It is, however,
و هو ايضاً
a message of courage as well.
رسالة تحث على الشجاعة
For a flower does not ask for anyone's permission to bloom.
لأن الزهرة لا تستأذن احداً لتزدهر
It was born to offer itself to the world.
و هي قد ولدت لتقدم نفسها للعالم
Fearless love is its nature.
الحب اللذي لا يخشى شيئاً هي طبيعتها
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)